<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>華生的珈琲館</title>
  
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://watsonhugo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-11-03T09:53:04.412Z</updated>
  <id>https://watsonhugo.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Tianchen</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Rise and Fall of Shanghai&#39;s Bookstore</title>
    <link href="https://watsonhugo.github.io/2019/11/03/shanghai-bookstore/"/>
    <id>https://watsonhugo.github.io/2019/11/03/shanghai-bookstore/</id>
    <published>2019-11-03T09:28:54.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-03T09:53:04.412Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Last week in Shanghai, an official directive has yet put another cultural recollection spot in jeopardy. Swatow Books, a small newsstand in Foochow Road was required by the authority to shut down as it is “unruly built”. The reason might be preposterous to an unintiated outsider, but quite common for the natives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you came two decades before to Shanghai and wanted to have some street-smart advices on bookstores, Foochow Road, I’m sure, would be definitely on your top list. The place, like Charing Cross in London or Chung-King South Road in Taipei, gathered the most major culture outlets of the city. In its salad days, roaming around for books, stationaries and curios was not only recreation for citizens, but also typical activities at weekends for students and professors, as it was practically impossible to find the title elsewhere if you can’t position it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to be one of them in early 2000s, at the eve of the Internet age when there are still several years for e-commerce to prosper, grubbing for favoured books and magazines on this road in some of the finest places I think the city can provide. Shanghai used to be a major cosmoplis during the nationalist years when magazines like &lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; were everywhere to be found and films released parallelly at the same time with North America. Its openness was completely devastated after the communist takeover. For ideaology’s sake, strict control has long been posed by the authoirty on the publications from overseas ordinary people can get access. However, as a history lover my desire to read foreign magazines has prompted me to explore further possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/sE9hr2n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jifeng&amp;#39;s memoir&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="bookstore" scheme="https://watsonhugo.github.io/tags/bookstore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>呂敬人書籍設計40年</title>
    <link href="https://watsonhugo.github.io/2018/10/07/2018-10-07/"/>
    <id>https://watsonhugo.github.io/2018/10/07/2018-10-07/</id>
    <published>2018-10-07T04:09:36.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-07T04:58:10.619Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/OrcwQNK.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;呂敬人書籍設計40年特展&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但凡愛讀點書的人，看到書的感覺總和不愛讀書的人有些不一樣。這是怎樣一種魔力？一時還真說不上來。閉上眼睛仔細想想，是紙上文字銳利的邊緣，油墨的芬芳，抑或是書頁摩挲的窸窣？大概都有吧。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;小時候對書籍的裝幀並不在意，只消飢渴地從書中汲取養分。長大以後卻對字體、封面、留白這些細節耿耿於懷。大陸市面上的書籍，大都泛泛，眼睛一亮者實在鳳毛麟角，而每每勾我魂魄的，基本都出自於寥寥可數的那幾位之手：呂敬人、陸智昌、朱贏椿，還有在台灣如雷貫耳的王志弘。他們的作品獨樹一幟，極具辨識度。最近在上海劉海粟美術館舉辦的「書藝問道——呂敬人書籍設計40年」展覽以及在衡山和集書店的講座帶我們從「改革開放」初期一路走來，歷數這位書籍設計大師的重要作品，窺看近40年來中國大陸書籍設計的變遷。&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="字體排印" scheme="https://watsonhugo.github.io/tags/%E5%AD%97%E9%AB%94%E6%8E%92%E5%8D%B0/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>日本的小學教育</title>
    <link href="https://watsonhugo.github.io/2018/09/24/2018-09-24/"/>
    <id>https://watsonhugo.github.io/2018/09/24/2018-09-24/</id>
    <published>2018-09-24T13:53:26.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-06T10:48:18.311Z</updated>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;在我們的傳統印象裡，日常生活中的日本人總是彬彬有禮，為人著想。這種印象不光來自於各類新聞報導、電視劇、文學作品中，我們似乎也能從日本觀光回來的人們那裡得到印證。這種情感確實發自內心還是虛情假意暫且不論，你不得不承認至少表面上的那套禮儀還是讓你如沐春風，心曠神怡。據說日本人從小就被教育凡事要懂得感恩，體恤他人。我不禁好奇，日本孩子從小接受的是怎樣的教育？這種教育制度的淵源為何？最近有兩本書可一探究竟。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/cEPJCVz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;《日本國立小學365天》&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;em&gt;《日本國立小學365天》&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;其中一本《&lt;a href=&quot;https://book.douban.com/subject/27175484/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;日本國立小學365天&lt;/a&gt;》於去年出版，由在日本大學任翻譯科教師的中國人所撰。作者兒子小學的大部分時間都在北京度過，六年級的時候來日本入東京當地國立小學接受了一年的教育。日本的小學要求學生寫日記記錄生活，孩子母親在此期間也頗多感悟，因此將這些感悟和孩子的日記匯集成這一本書。另一本《&lt;a href=&quot;https://book.douban.com/subject/28381105/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;教養與文明&lt;/a&gt;》，是在日本唸過碩士的中國人所作的研究而成。其實這本書初版於2012年，去年再版，打算有空看完再作介紹。最近我剛讀完從&lt;code&gt;多抓魚&lt;/code&gt;上淘來的第一本書，下面是讀書時的一些筆記：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;學校對家長的要求是很具體的，在學年初就會公佈整個學年的日程表，家長需要為子女購買學具、治裝等，規定細緻詳盡，還有上學的路線、各類活動的安排。防災帽是日本小學的一大特色。因為日本是災難頻發的國家，佩戴防災帽的要求不僅旨在從小樹立學生的防災意識，也確實堅固耐用，具有實際意義。每週有一日學校不提供午餐，學生各自帶來母親準備的便當在午餐室四人圍一桌共同用餐。班主任每天輪換不同餐桌與學生一起吃飯，這樣的形式保證了老師與學生間充分交流的機會。老師和學生更像是朋友，老師和學生共同成長。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;開學之初老師便對學生說：&lt;strong&gt;上學的目標是交100個朋友。&lt;/strong&gt;日本小學注重培養孩子的個性。&lt;strong&gt;做得和別人一樣等於沒做，只有做到和別人不一樣才有可能得到認可。&lt;/strong&gt;這似乎和我們對日本的傳統認識有些不一樣吧？日本不是都要服從上級嗎？書中是這麼說的：「日本的集體意識是建立在個性的基礎之上的，追求在集體中發揮個性。」調皮的學生才風光，乖乖女按部就班沒有市場。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="日本" scheme="https://watsonhugo.github.io/tags/%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC/"/>
    
      <category term="教育" scheme="https://watsonhugo.github.io/tags/%E6%95%99%E8%82%B2/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
